Finding Aid for Jacob D. Brook papers, 1886-1954
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jacob D. Brook papers 1886-1954
Brook, Jacob D. (Jacob Daniel), 1876-1956.
1 oversize folders
3 linear feet
85489 Aa 2; UAl
Grandville, Kent County, Michigan, physician and public health official. Family and professional correspondence and other materials relating to his medical career, especially his education at the Detroit College of Medicine, private practice in Kent County, and work with professional organizations, including the Michigan State Medical Society and the Michigan Public Health Association; also material relating to his interest in the Reformed Church of Grandville; miscellaneous papers of father, Dirk Broek, and sister, Christina S. Broek; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Russell DeJong (donor 2380 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born in Cleveland, Ohio, in 1876, Jacob Daniel Brook moved with his family to the community of Grandville in Kent County, Michigan; and it was to this area that he returned when he completed his medical education at the Detroit College of Medicine (1902).
Following his graduation, Brook worked successively as the Health Officer of Wyoming Township in Kent County (1904-1930), and as Kent County Health Officer (1931-1954). Considered by many as a pioneer in preventative public health, Brook worked to establish clinics for immunization against diphtheria and whooping cough. In 1910, Brook brought suit against the city of Grand Rapids for what he considered the pollution of Grandville's water system.
Though his medical career centered in Grandville, Brook held important positions in various professional organizations. He was president of the Grand Rapids Academy of Medicine (1914), and the Kent County Medical Society (1915). He was also involved in the Michigan Public Health Association (president in 1937), the Michigan State Medical Society (president in 1929), and the State Board of Registration in Medicine (president in 1940). In addition, for 28 consecutive years (1907-1935), Brook served as delegate to the Michigan State Medical Society; and for 21 years (1917-1938), he was a delegate to the annual meeting of the American Medical Association. In this latter capacity, Brook exerted his influence within the A.M.A. on the issue of birth control (1935).
The Jacob Daniel Brook Collection reflects the activities of a man whose life was committed to the cause of medicine and public health. The collection has been arranged into four series: Correspondence, Professional and personal materials, Broek Family, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Central Reformed Church (Grandville, Mich.); Detroit College of Medicine.; Grandville (Mich.); Kent County (Mich.); Medicine--Michigan.; Michigan Public Health Association.; Michigan State Public Health Association.; Moody Bible Institute.; Physicians--Michigan--Grandville.; Public health--Michigan.; Reformed Church--Michigan--Grandville.; Travelers.; Wheeler, Clara Marian, 1861-1946.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Broek family.; Brook, Jacob D. (Jacob Daniel), 1876-1956.; Central Reformed Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Churches--Michigan--Grandville.; Detroit College of Medicine.; Dwellings--Michigan--Grandville.; First Reformed Church (Grandville, Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Churches.; Grandville (Mich.)--Churches.; Grandville (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Grandville (Mich.)--Streets.; Health care.; Hope College.; Medical education.; Polkton (Mich.: Township); Reformed Church in America.; Streets--Michigan--Grandville.; Zeeland (Mich.)
Contributors:
Broek, Christina S.; Broek, Dirk.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
    (file no. 1)
  - 1886-1900 (Box 1)
    (file no. 2)
  - 1901 (Box 1)
    (file no. 3)
  - 1902 (Box 1)
    (file no. 4)
  - 1903 (Box 1)
    (file no. 5)
  - 1905 (Box 1)
    (file no. 6)
  - 1906 (Box 1)
    (file no. 7)
  - 1908 (Box 1)
    (file no. 8)
  - 1909 (Box 1)
    (file no. 9)
  - 1910 (Box 1)
    (file no. 10)
  - 1914 (Box 1)
    (file no. 11)
  - 1915 (Box 1)
    (file no. 12)
  - 1916 (Box 1)
    (file no. 13)
  - 1917 (Box 1)
    (file no. 14)
  - 1918 (Box 1)
    (file no. 15)
  - 1919 (Box 1)
    (file no. 16)
  - 1920 (Box 1)
    (file no. 17)
  - 1921 (Box 1)
    (file no. 18)
  - 1922 (Box 1)
    (file no. 19)
  - January-April 1923 (Box 1)
    (file no. 20)
  - May-November 1923 (Box 1)
    (file no. 21)
  - December 1923 (Box 1)
    (file no. 22)
  - 1924 (Box 1)
    (file no. 22a)
  - 1925 (Box 1)
    (file no. 23)
  - 1926 (Box 1)
    (file no. 24)
  - January-June 1927 (Box 1)
    (file no. 25)
  - July-December 1927 (Box 1)
    (file no. 26)
  - 1928 (Box 1)
    (file no. 27)
  - January-April 1929 (Box 1)
    (file no. 28)
  - May-October 1929 (Box 1)
    (file no. 29)
  - November-December 1929 (Box 1)
    (file no. 30)
  - January-March 1930 (Box 1)
    (file no. 31)
  - April-June 1930 (Box 1)
    (file no. 32)
  - July-October 1930 (Box 1)
    (file no. 33)
  - November-December 1930 (Box 1)
    (file no. 34)
  - 1931 (Box 1)
    (file no. 35)
  - January-May 1932 (Box 1)
    (file no. 36)
  - June-December 1932 (Box 1)
    (file no. 37)
  - 1933 (Box 1)
    (file no. 38)
  - January-April 1934 (Box 1)
    (file no. 39)
  - May-December 1934 (Box 1)
    (file no. 40)
  - January-April 1935 (Box 1)
    (file no. 41)
  - May-August 1935 (Box 1)
    (file no. 42)
  - September-December 1935 (Box 1)
    (file no. 43)
  - January-March 1936 (Box 1)
    (file no. 44)
  - April-December 1936 (Box 1)
    (file no. 45)
  - January-May 1937 (Box 1)
    (file no. 46)
  - June-December 1937 (Box 1)
    (file no. 47)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
    (file no. 48)
  - January-July 1939 (Box 1)
    (file no. 49)
  - August-December 1939 (Box 1)
    (file no. 50)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
    (file no. 51)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
    (file no. 52)
  - 1942 (Box 1)
    (file no. 53)
  - 1943 (Box 1)
    (file no. 54)
  - 1944 (Box 1)
    (file no. 55)
  - 1945 (Box 1)
    (file no. 56)
  - 1946 (Box 1)
    (file no. 57)
  - 1950 (Box 1)
    (file no. 58)
  - 1951 (Box 1)
    (file no. 59)
  - 1952 (Box 1)
    (file no. 60)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
    (file no. 61)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
    (file no. 62)
- Professional and personal materials
  In addition to personal and professional correspondence, the collection includes professional and personal materials, such as his student notebooks from the Detroit College of Medicine, copies and drafts of his speeches on medical topics, medical reports, published articles, newspaper clippings about Brook and his activities, and scattered medical data. There is also information about other phases of Brook's life in Grandville, particularly his membership in the Grandville Reformed Church, and his work with the Grandville Board of Education.
  - Drafts of reports to Michigan State Medical Society 1920-1938 (Box 2)
    (file no. 63, 64)
  - Articles published by J.D. Brook (Box 2)
    (file no. 65)
  - Drafts of speeches of J.D. Brook (Box 2)
    (file no. 66)
  - Miscellaneous papers of J.D. Brook (Box 2)
    (file no. 67)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 2)
    (file no. 67a)
  - Medical data compiled by J.D. Brook (Box 2)
    (file no. 68)
  - Student notes of J.D. Brook (Box 2)
    (file no. 69)
  - Tax returns of J.D. Brook 1918-1922, 1925-1926 (Box 2)
    (file no. 70)
  - (Medical) Examination records for Grand Camp Knights of the Maccabees 1893-1910 (Box 2)
    (file no. 71)
  - (Medical) Examination records for Great Hive Ladies of the Maccabees 1902-1907 (Box 2)
    (file no. 72)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings on J.D. Brook 1902-1956 (Box 2)
    (file nos. 73, 74)
  - Scrapbook kept by office staff of Kent Co. Health Department 1937-1950 (Box 2)
  - Notebooks of J.D. Brook while student at Detroit College of Medicine 1898-1902, 30 volumes (Box 2)
- Broek family
  With the Brook papers, the researcher will find miscellaneous information about other members of the Brook or Broek family. Early in his life, Brook had changed from the family name of Broek. The reasons for the change are not clear. The collection includes some papers of J.C. Brook's father, the Reverend Dirk Broek (1835-1903), early settler of Holland, Michigan, and minister of the First Reformed Church of Grandville. These papers include church related materials, such as marriage certificates, sermon materials, and a diary. There is also some of his correspondence with family and friends. Another part of the collection relates to the life and career of Jacob Brook's sister, Christina S. Broek. A graduate of Moody Institute, Christina was a Grandville grammar school teacher. She was also a correspondent of Clara M. Wheeler regarding the work of the Grandville Sunday School Association. An interesting part of her papers is a diary of a trip to Europe on the eve of World War I.
  - History of Broek family and memorials on death of Harm Broek 1809-1903 (Box 3)
    (file no. 75)
  - Correspondence and sermons of Rev. Dirk Broek (Box 3)
    (file no. 76)
  - Record of marriages performed by Rev. Dirk Broek 1865-1903 (Box 3)
    (file no. 77)
  - Central Reformed Church (Grandville) records of Rev. Dirk Broek 1894-1903 (Box 3)
    (file no. 78, 79)
  - Diary of Reverend Dirk Broek 1866 and list of letters written, 1899-1903 (Box 3)
    (file no. 80)
  - Letters and printed material by and about Albertus T. Broek (Box 3)
    (file no. 81)
  - Letters and printed material by and about John V. Broek (Box 3)
    (file no. 82)
  - Correspondence of Christina Broek 1897-1919 (Box 3)
    (file no. 83)
  - Correspondence of Christina Broek 1920-1930 (Box 3)
    (file no. 84)
  - Correspondence of Christina Broek 1931-1943 (Box 3)
    (file no. 85)
  - Christina Broek's European trip 1914 (Box 3)
    (file no. 86, 87)
  - Newspaper clippings and miscellaneous papers of Christina Broek (Box 3)
    (file no. 88)
  - Diaries 1911, 1914, 1915 and notes of Moody Institute, 1911 of Christina Broek (Box 3)
    (file no. 89)
  - Diary of Christina Broek 1932-1941 (Box 3)
    (file no. 90)
  - Notes taken by Christina Broek on Sunday School course given by Clara Wheeler 1922 (Box 3)
    (file no. 91)
  - Scrapbook of Madge Brook with clippings of auto trip in Michigan circa 1920s (Box 3)
    (file no. 92)
  - Broek family miscellaneous papers (Box 3)
    (file no. 93)
  - Unidentified and non-family 1907-1937 (Box 3)
    (file no. 94)
  - Family miscellanea (Box 3)
    (file no. 94a)
  - Grandville church miscellanea (Box 3)
    (file no. 94b)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes portraits of Brook and family members; photos relating to his education at the Detroit College of Medicine; views of buildings and activities of the First Reformed Church of Grandville, and other photographs of Grandville and Reformed Church groups.
  - Jacob D. Brook, early photos 1900-1920 (Box 3)
    - 1900-1920
      (file no. 95)
    - 1920-circa 1950
      (file no. 96)
      (see also oversize folder UAl)
  - Albertus T. Broek (Box 3)
    (file no. 97)
  - Christina Broek (Box 3)
    (file no. 98)
  - John Y. Broek (Box 3)
    (file no. 99)
  - Broek family. Parents, grandparents of John D. Broek (Box 3)
    (file no. 100)
  - Broek family. Other members (Box 3)
    (file no. 101)
  - Central Reformed Church Consistory, Grand Rapids 1941 (Box 3)
    (file no. 102)
  - Detroit College of Medicine (Box 3)
    (file no. 103)
  - Grand River classis (Box 3)
    (file no. 104)
  - Grandville, Mich. First Reformed Church and parsonage (Box 3)
    (file no. 105)
  - Grandville, Mich. Other photos (Box 3)
    (file no. 106)
  - Hope College students and faculty 1884 (Box 3)
    (file no. 107)
  - Parsonage, Polkton, Mich. (Box 3)
    (file no. 108)
  - Smallpox photos (Box 3)
    (file no. 109)
  - Zeeland, Mich., early settlers (Box 3)
    (file no. 110)